Guide to the Communications Workers of America Oral History Project Records WAG.378
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Ralph Maly, 2024; TW_WAG_378_ER_25
  Ralph Maly went to work at AT&T's Western Electric factory in Buffalo, NY in 1966 at age 19. From day one, he had union in his bones, joining Local 1162 and soon becoming the local organizer. Maly went on to organize Western Electric factories in Pleasanton, CA; Vancouver, WA; Dallas, TX; and Atlanta, GA. When the Buffalo factory closed, Maly transferred to a Western Electric facility in Atlanta, where he was elected Local 3263 president in 1985. Maly joined the CWA staff four years later, leading bargaining with Lucent Technologies (the spin-off from AT&T's Western Electric subsidiary), later merged with Alcatel and bought by Nokia. Maly's career spanned the growth and ultimate closing of the factories that he helped organize into the union.
- Sandy Rusher, 2024; TW_WAG_378_ER_26
  Sandy Rusher helped tens of thousands of workers join CWA during her more than thirty years as an CWA organizer, first with the Texas State Employees Union (TSEU), then District 6 Organizing Director, and CWA national Organizing Director. At TSEU, she pioneered (with Danny Fetonte), the CWA model of organization of state workers without collective bargaining coverage. Rusher continued to work with Fetonte and District 6 vice-president Vic Crawley on a bargain to organize "Five Years to Card Check" campaign that won majority sign-up (card check)/neutrality for SBC (and after multiple mergers, AT&T) wireless workers. Among her many organizing achievements, Rusher led the long, ultimately successful campaign to support American Airlines customer service employees win their union.
- Sara Nelson, 2024; TW_WAG_378_ER_27
  Sara Nelson was elected president of the Association of Flight Attendants/CWA in 2014, the position she held at the time of this interview. The AFA joined CWA in 2003, and together with CWA's representation of customer service workers at American and other airlines, CWA now represents more than 75,000 aviation employees. Nelson has been a union Flight Attendant since 1996 when she started flying at United Airlines. During her tenure, Nelson negotiated many pathbreaking contracts and successfully moved federal legislation to improve job security, compensation, and a healthy and safe work environment for her members. During the Covid-19 pandemic that grounded airline travel, she played a key role in passage of a $54 billion congressional Covid relief package that provided pay, health care, and other benefits to aviation workers and saved the industry from collapse.
- Velvet Hawthorne, 2024; TW_WAG_378_ER_28
  Velvet Hawthorne, who worked in a US Airways call center in Winston-Salem, North Carolina, led the organizing campaign to bring 10,000 US Airways customer service employees into CWA. After three contested elections, the union was finally certified in 1999 and ratified the first contract that year. Hawthorne was appointed staff representative with responsibility for training stewards for the new union. She negotiated breakthrough contracts which faced challenges in response to mergers (American Airlines and America West) and shutdowns in the airline industry after 9/11 and the COVID pandemic.
- Yvette Herrera, 2024; TW_WAG_378_ER_29
  Yvette Herrera held many positions, beginning in the former District 5 office. In 1987 she moved to Washington, D.C. to serve as the Education and Mobilization Director, after which she served as Assistant to the Executive Vice President and later Assistant to the President. Herrera was born in Cuba, and was responsible for the Minority Leadership Institute for 26 years, working closely with former CWA Human Rights Directors Drew Clark, Mary Mays Carroll, Leslie Jackson, and Gwend Johnson. Herrera also served on the national board of the Labor Council for Latin American Advancement (LCLAA), and as the President of the International Labor Rights Forum.